So once you've developed your initial issue tree,
how can you test it and improve it?
One tool that we can use to help test or improve upon our issue tree
is something we call MECE.
So what is MECE? Mutually exclusive, collectively exhaustive.
No overlaps, no gaps. When we think about mutually exclusive,
we want to make sure there's no overlap in the issues —
so if there's an issue, it only appears in one branch of that tree.
When we think about collectively exhaustive, this is making sure there are no gaps —
so it's making sure that, at the right-hand side of the tree,
all of the issues that we've identified are fully captured there,
and we've effectively broadened the scope of our solutions.
So let's use an example of what is MECE and what is not MECE.
So if I think about what is MECE — if I'm defining my problem to be:
how do I break down profitability? I may decompose my tree
into the revenue drivers and the cost drivers.
Let me give you some examples of what is not MECE, in terms of a list.
So if my list included breakfast, lunch and meals —
well, that wouldn't be MECE, because
breakfast and lunch are part of meals. Therefore it's not mutually exclusive,
because there's an overlap in the two different issues.
If I was explaining how a traffic light worked to my son
and I said there are green lights and red lights —
well, I've not been collectively exhaustive,
because I haven't mentioned the yellow lights.
So there are a couple of tips on how best to get your issue tree to be MECE.
Number one: think about how you can get as much input as possible,
particularly from experts — and the collective wisdom
will oftentimes lead to a superior answer
versus what one person can come up with themselves.
And with that, it's an exercise that really benefits from an iterative process.
Don't think that you need to get the exact right answer out of the gate.
Better to get an
answer that's 80% of the way there, and then test and iterate that as you go —
rather than over-invest or spend too much time up front
trying to get to the perfect solution.
So once you've got your tree as close to MECE as you think you can,
the next step is prioritisation.
And this is where it's really important to think about the sequencing.
And one of the traps people sometimes fall into
is eliminating items on the issue tree too early.
The best way to do it is to have a more collectively exhaustive issue tree,
so you have all the issues laid out in front of you,
and then to prioritise —
and think about not only which issues you want to tackle first,
but what branches of the tree may not apply.
So, prioritising too early
sometimes links back to the definition phase of the problem statement,
where you're thinking about the scope of the solution set.
And so if the problem you're trying to solve is:
how do we grow revenue? You might think about what we can do in terms of price,
or what we can do in terms of volume, right — selling more widgets, if you will.
But another way to drive revenue growth might be through acquisition, right?
Acquiring another company and basically combining the revenue of the two entities.
It may be the case that acquisitions are off the table
because of budget constraints or others,
but if you don't include that as an option in terms of growing revenue,
you may too early, and too narrowly, define the scope of your solution set —
and that should get to the right answer.